Register of the Congress of Racial Equality. Washington Interracial Workshop: Records, 1942-1956
Wisconsin Historical Society
Congress of Racial Equality. Washington Interracial Workshop: Records, 1942-1956
Congress of Racial Equality. Washington Interracial Workshop
Mss 223
1.0 c.f. (3 archives boxes)
Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Records of the Washington Interracial Workshop, the Washington, D.C., CORE affiliate (1949-1955), consisting of operational files and information on various desegregation campaigns. Of these, the year-long effort to integrate the Rosedale Playground is best represented, in one box of correspondence, minutes, lists, reports, research and legal material, publicity, and clippings. Within the operational files, correspondence, a constitution, minutes, reports to national headquarters, and publications provide an overview of the workshop's role in civil rights activities generally. The latter section also includes information about related civil rights activities of chairman Albert Mindlin, 1953-1955.
The Washington Interracial Workshop, which affiliated with the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) in 1949, began in 1947 as a summer workshop sponsored by CORE and the Fellowship of Reconciliation (FOR). The summer program attracted a dozen persons from the District of Columbia and other states throughout the United States. Local participants considered the Workshop so successful that they formed a separate, permanent organization dedicated to abolishing segregation in the nation's capital. Both this organization and the summer workshops, which CORE and FOR continued to sponsor every year, operated by the CORE principles of interracial membership, direct action, and non-violent tactics. Membership fluctuated between ten and twenty people.
Under the chairmanship of Lynn Seiter from 1947 to 1948, the Workshop picketed and leafleted patrons of segregated facilities at the Y.M.C.A., the Greyhound Bus Terminal, and public swimming pools in the nation's capital. When Don Coan took over the chairmanship in April 1949, the Workshop began a lengthy struggle to integrate D.C. movie theatres that only ended in April 1951; Coan also moved to make eating places and recreational facilities available to people of all races. In the spring of 1951 Albert Mindlin succeeded Coan and spearheaded efforts to integrate Washington's playgrounds. The Rosedale Playground campaign, which is the best documented in these papers, became a city-wide issue after a black child drowned while swimming in the playground pool after hours on June 22, 1952. The playground was not opened to blacks until October 28 of that year.
The Workshop gradually became inactive after 1953, and Mindlin became more absorbed in national CORE disputes. Following ineffective attempts to integrate the Metropolitan Police Boys Club, the Workshop disbanded on March 13, 1955. In the mid-1960's, the Washington CORE chapter was reactivated.
The records of the Washington Interracial Workshop, 1942-1956 (primarily 1948-1956), include information on its general structure and operations as well as on specific activities, especially the Rosedale Playground campaign.
The general operations records include a constitution, minutes, general correspondence, correspondence and reports to national CORE, publications, and lists of attendance at meetings and of potential donors. These give a very sketchy overview of the Workshop's role in civil rights work in the period 1948-1956. The papers for 1953-1956 give more information about Albert Mindlin's civil rights activities than those of the Workshop.
The records of specific activities include information on the Council for Civil Rights in the Nation's Capital, on campaigns to integrate Washington's Fire Department, hotels, the Metropolitan Police Boys Club, and playgrounds. The year-long struggle to open the Rosedale Playground is the most fully documented aspect of the Workshop's activities and includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, minutes and attendance lists of meetings, reports, research and legal material, publicity information, and clippings.
Additional information on the Washington Interracial Workshop can be found in the records of national CORE (Mss 14), series 3, box 9, folder 1 and box 13, folders 5-7.
Administrative/Restriction Information
Presented by Albert Mindlin, Bethesda, Maryland, in January, February, and March of 1972. M72-9, M72-31, M72-95
Contents List
- General Operations
  - Constitution, 1949, Feb. 17-1950, April 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1948, March 2-1951, July 26; 1954, June 7-Dec. 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, General
    - 1947, July 18-1948, June 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1949, Jan. 5-Dec. 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1950, Jan. 5-Aug. 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1951, Oct. 23-1955, Oct. 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and Reports to National CORE, 1950, March 8-1954, Oct. 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter, 1947, Aug. 13-1955, March 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1947-1954, March (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Attendance Lists, 1950, Nov. 16-1953, Jan. 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lists of Potential Donors, 1950, Sept. 1; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Activities
  - Council for Civil Rights in the Nation's Capital, 1947, Aug.-1948, April 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fire Department, 1951, Nov. 26-1952, Aug. 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hotels, 1953, Sept. 22-1955, Feb. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Metropolitan Police Boys Club, 1952-1956, April 14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rosedale Playground
    - Correspondence
      - 1951, June 15; 1952, Jan. 28-April 30 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1952, May 1-Sept. 26 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 1952, Oct. 3-Dec. 5 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Meetings
      - Minutes, 1951, March 22-1953, June 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Attendance, 1952, April 9-June 18; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Reports
      - Pilgrimage, 1951, Oct.-1952, July (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1951, Oct. 22-1953, Jan. 25 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Research Material
      - 1942-1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1952; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Legal Material, 1952, Jan. 28-1953, Oct. 7; undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Publicity, 1952, June 22-July 14; undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Clippings, unsorted, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Clippings, unsorted, undated, continued (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Schools, 1952, Oct. 12-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Theatres
    - Trans Lux, 1949, June 5-Dec. 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General, 1948, May 5-1951, May 16 (Box 3, Folder 4)